<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Jan Heinrich Reimer | Harry Scells</title><link>/authors/jan-heinrich-reimer/</link><atom:link href="/authors/jan-heinrich-reimer/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Jan Heinrich Reimer</description><generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 11 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>/media/icon_hu33ac2647be7de12c09d025d9374b4e08_2029_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>Jan Heinrich Reimer</title><link>/authors/jan-heinrich-reimer/</link></image><item><title>Resources for Combining Teaching and Research in Information Retrieval Coursework</title><link>/publication/sigir2024_teaching/</link><pubDate>Thu, 11 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/publication/sigir2024_teaching/</guid><description>&lt;div class="alert alert-note">
&lt;div>
&lt;strong>Nominated for best resource paper award!&lt;/strong>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>A recent study showed that students in IR courses are especially motivated and learn more effectively when they participate in shared tasks as part of their coursework. To support teachers in integrating such activities, we present Web IDE-based applications and tutorials that employ TIREx and ir_datasets to cover the process of a typical shared task in IR: from creating test collections over developing retrieval systems to making relevance judgments and finally statistically analyzing the results. Using our tools, students can gain hands-on experience with empirical IR research by working on some current shared task, by working on earlier collections, or by creating new ones. Our experiences in implementing the cor- responding teaching concept in four IR courses at two universities confirm that students are very motivated to conduct research, and we also find that some of the resulting artifacts (e.g., students’ test collections and retrieval approaches) are of really good quality.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The Archive Query Log: Mining Millions of Search Result Pages of Hundreds of Search Engines from 25 Years of Web Archives</title><link>/publication/sigir2023_aql/</link><pubDate>Wed, 19 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/publication/sigir2023_aql/</guid><description>&lt;p>The Archive Query Log (AQL) is a previously unused, comprehensive query log collected at the Internet Archive over the last 25 years. Its first version includes 356 million queries, 137 million search result pages, and 1.4 billion search results across 550 search providers. Although many query logs have been studied in the literature, the search providers that own them generally do not publish their logs to protect user privacy and vital business data. Of the few query logs publicly available, none combines size, scope, and diversity. The AQL is the first to do so, enabling research on new retrieval models and (diachronic) search engine analyses. Provided in a privacy-preserving manner, it promotes open research as well as more transparency and accountability in the search industry.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>