<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Daniel Locke | Harry Scells</title>
    <link>//localhost:1313/authors/daniel-locke/</link>
      <atom:link href="//localhost:1313/authors/daniel-locke/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Daniel Locke</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>//localhost:1313/media/icon_hu33ac2647be7de12c09d025d9374b4e08_2029_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Daniel Locke</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/authors/daniel-locke/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>MeSH Term Suggestion for Systematic Review Literature Search</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/publication/adcs2021_mesh/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/publication/adcs2021_mesh/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Awarded Best Student Paper!&lt;/strong&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;High-quality medical systematic reviews require comprehensive literature searches to ensure the recommendations and outcomes are sufficiently reliable. Indeed, searching for relevant medical literature is a key phase in constructing systematic reviews and often involves domain (medical researchers) and search (information specialists) experts in developing the search queries. Queries in this context are highly complex, based on Boolean logic, include free-text terms and index terms from standardised terminologies (e.g., MeSH), and are difficult and time-consuming to build. The use of MeSH terms, in particular, has been shown to improve the quality of the search results. However, identifying the correct MeSH terms to include in a query is difficult: information experts are often unfamiliar with the MeSH database and unsure about the appropriateness of MeSH terms for a query. Naturally, the full value of the MeSH terminology is often not fully exploited.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paper investigates methods to suggest MeSH terms based on an initial Boolean query that includes only free-text terms. These methods promise to automatically identify highly effective MeSH terms for inclusion in a systematic review query. Our study contributes an empirical evaluation of several MeSH term suggestion methods. We perform an extensive analysis of the retrieval, ranking, and refinement of MeSH term suggestions for each method and how these suggestions impact the effectiveness of Boolean queries.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An Information Retrieval Experiment Framework for Domain Specific Applications</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/publication/sigir2018_framework/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/publication/sigir2018_framework/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
