<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Leif Azzopardi | Harry Scells</title><link>/authors/leif-azzopardi/</link><atom:link href="/authors/leif-azzopardi/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Leif Azzopardi</description><generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>/media/icon_hu33ac2647be7de12c09d025d9374b4e08_2029_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>Leif Azzopardi</title><link>/authors/leif-azzopardi/</link></image><item><title>A Test Collection for Evaluating Retrieval of Studies for Inclusion in Systematic Reviews</title><link>/publication/sigir2017_collection/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/publication/sigir2017_collection/</guid><description>&lt;p>We introduce a test collection for evaluating the effectiveness of different methods used to retrieve research studies for inclusion in systematic reviews. Systematic reviews appraise and synthesise studies that meet specific inclusion criteria. Systematic reviews intended for a biomedical science audience use boolean queries with many, often complex, search clauses to retrieve studies; these are then manually screened to determine eligibility for inclusion in the review. This process is expensive and time consuming. The development of systems that improve retrieval effectiveness will have an immediate impact by reducing the complexity and resources required for this process. Our test collection consists of approximately 26 million research studies extracted from the freely available MEDLINE database, 94 review (query) topics extracted from Cochrane systematic reviews, and corresponding relevance assessments. Tasks for which the collection can be used for information retrieval system evaluation are described and the use of the collection to evaluate common baselines within one such task is demonstrated. See the links to this side of this page for links to the paper and to download the collection.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>