<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Maik Fröbe | Harry Scells</title><link>https://scells.me/authors/maik-frobe/</link><atom:link href="https://scells.me/authors/maik-frobe/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Maik Fröbe</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://scells.me/media/icon_hu33ac2647be7de12c09d025d9374b4e08_2029_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>Maik Fröbe</title><link>https://scells.me/authors/maik-frobe/</link></image><item><title>Evaluating Generative Ad Hoc Information Retrieval</title><link>https://scells.me/publication/arxiv2023_evaluating/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://scells.me/publication/arxiv2023_evaluating/</guid><description>&lt;p>Recent advances in large language models have enabled the development of viable generative information retrieval systems. A generative retrieval system returns a grounded generated text in response to an information need instead of the traditional document ranking. Quantifying the utility of these types of responses is essential for evaluating generative retrieval systems. As the established evaluation methodology for ranking-based ad hoc retrieval may seem unsuitable for generative retrieval, new approaches for reliable, repeatable, and reproducible experimentation are required. In this paper, we survey the relevant information retrieval and natural language processing literature, identify search tasks and system architectures in generative retrieval, develop a corresponding user model, and study its operationalization. This theoretical analysis provides a foundation and new insights for the evaluation of generative ad hoc retrieval systems.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The Archive Query Log: Mining Millions of Search Result Pages of Hundreds of Search Engines from 25 Years of Web Archives</title><link>https://scells.me/publication/sigir2023_aql/</link><pubDate>Wed, 19 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://scells.me/publication/sigir2023_aql/</guid><description>&lt;p>The Archive Query Log (AQL) is a previously unused, comprehensive query log collected at the Internet Archive over the last 25 years. Its first version includes 356 million queries, 137 million search result pages, and 1.4 billion search results across 550 search providers. Although many query logs have been studied in the literature, the search providers that own them generally do not publish their logs to protect user privacy and vital business data. Of the few query logs publicly available, none combines size, scope, and diversity. The AQL is the first to do so, enabling research on new retrieval models and (diachronic) search engine analyses. Provided in a privacy-preserving manner, it promotes open research as well as more transparency and accountability in the search industry.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>